<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the king and queen at White-Hall, December 13th. 1691 by Edward Pelling ... ; published by Her Majesties special command.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12851894</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12851894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53981)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1038:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the king and queen at White-Hall, December 13th. 1691 by Edward Pelling ... ; published by Her Majesties special command.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print showthrough with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N. Y.) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Conscience, Examination of.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94547:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:94547:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> A SERMON Preached before the King &amp; Queen
AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>December 13th.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to Their
Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Her Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Everingham</hi> at the
<hi>Star</hi> near the <hi>Weſt End of</hi> St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:94547:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94547:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING and QUEEN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Acts XXIV. 16.</bibl>
               <q>And herein do I Exerciſe my ſelf, to have always a
Conſcience void of offence toward God and toward Man.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE were the words of the Great Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
when he was Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Caeſarea;</hi> when <hi>Ananias</hi> and the
Elders were Parties to accuſe him; when the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Tertullus</hi> was
Counſel to proſecute him; when <hi>Felix</hi> was the Judge, and many
deſperate Witneſſes were ready to depoſe the falſeſt things
againſt him; in Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94547:3"/> ſo dangerous, that no
way ſeem'd open for Innocence to eſcape; this was the Apoſtles Defence
and Comfort, the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience. <hi>This</hi> (ſaid he)
<hi>I confeſs, that after the way which the Jews call Hereſy, ſo
worſhip I the God of my Fathers, believing all things which are written in
the Law and the Prophets; and have Hope towards God, which they themſelves
alſo allow, that there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the Dead: And herein do
I exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe my ſelf, to have always a Conſcience void of offence toward
God and toward Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may rightly underſtand this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we muſt
conſider a little, what it is to have <hi>a Conſcience void of
offence,</hi> which was the ground of the Apoſtle's Plea.</p>
            <p>Conſcience in general, ſignifies a Man's Judgment or Opinion,
as it relates to Action. That Noble Faculty of the Soul; the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
when it looks and enquires into things, whether they be <hi>True</hi> or
<hi>Falſe,</hi> is fuly called the <hi>Speculative Judgement:</hi> But when
it is employed about ſomething that is to be done, and examines will them in
he <hi>Good</hi> or <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94547:3"/> Evil, it is called by Moraliſts, the
<hi>Practick Judgment;</hi> and by Divines <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And the
Office of Conſcience is two-fold; to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect one in acting, and then to
paſs a Cenſure up on his Actions: Before the thing is done, Conſcience
ſerves as a Tutor to adviſe and teach; and after the Fact is over, it
ſerves as a Judge, either to acquit, or to condemn him for it.</p>
            <p>So that to have a <hi>Conſcience void of Offence,</hi> is in the
Apoſtle's ſenſe, to be powerfully go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by one's Conſcience in the
faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Duty; and ſo to follow the Light which is in his
Underſtanding, as not to fall into any known Sin, nor to act any thing which
will gall and wound his Mind in the conſequence. When a Man is conſcious to
himſelf, that according to the beſt of his Endeavours, he has been careful
to expreſs his Duty to God and Man; when his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience governs him
rightly, and makes him chearful; when it gives him true Advice, and Spiritual
Comfort; when it is Honeſt in it's Directions, and Delightful in it's
Rewards; <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94547:4"/> then he may be rightly ſaid to have a
<hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of Offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This the Apoſtle proteſted now in open Court, was his
conſtant Exerciſe: But this muſt be underſtood chiefly of the time
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Converſion, to Chriſtianity. For while he was yet a <hi>Jew</hi>
and a zealous <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee,</hi> his Conſcience was not void of all
Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: We know what his Sins were, and with what Penitence and Freedom he
lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them afterwards. Yet this is to be ſaid on his behalf, that for
ought we find, he was a Man of ſincere Intentions all along. Tho' he was
zealous for the Law, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtianity, and was guilty of the
Blood of the Proto-martyr St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> yet in all this he followed his
Judgment at that time. His great fault was not ſo much in his Will as in his
Underſtanding: His Prejudices were ſtrong and powerful; his Education
carry'd a mighty hand over him, and the concurrent Zeal of the Prieſts and
Elders did very much help to inflame him ſtill; ſo that he thought in his
Conſcience he was bound to do many things contrary <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94547:4"/> to the
Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as he ſeriouſly and ſolemnly profeſſed,
<hi>Act.</hi> 26. 9. He was a ſad Example of Humane Infirmity: And as we
learn by it, to extend our Charity and Compaſſion to thoſe whoſe
Conſciences are miſ-lead after that manner; ſo He himſelf became a
great Object of God's Compaſſion; his Errors ſerv'd to leſſen his
Guilt; and <hi>he obtained Mercy, becauſe he ſinned ignorantly in
Unbelief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 13.</p>
            <p>But when he came to be throughly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the Son of
Righteouſneſs, and his Conſcience was ſet to rights, it was his
ſtedfaſt Reſolution and fixt Endeavour to keep it more in Charity than
the Apple of his Eye: As a Man that has once broken his Bones by chance, is
very careful leſt he ſlip again; ſo was the Apoſtle after his
Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, induſtriouſly bent upon keeping his Conſcience from every
the leaſt Wound or Blow. He valued no Stripes, as long as they did not touch
that tender Part. Defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, Impriſonment, the grimeſt Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the
greateſt Difficulties, Death it ſelf with all its ghaſtly and frightful
Retinue; <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94547:5"/> all was welcome to Him, as long as he could keep
that Darling in his boſom, his <hi>Conſcience, void of Offence toward God
and toward Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhews us all what ought to be the great Care and
Buſineſs of our whole Life; in every particular ſtill to have a very
tender Regard and Care of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; and whatever we neglect or
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get amidſt the Hurries of this troubleſome World, never to let this
great Care ſlip out of our Minds. For whether Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be well or ill
kept, a Man ſhall be ſure to hear of it at laſt; he will certainly find
the Iſſues and Effects of it at home; let him take what courſe he
pleaſes, his Conſcience will bear him Company, and in the end prove his
Comfort, or his Plague.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, a Man's Conſcience may not accuſe him or fly upon
him preſently: How Evil ſoever it be, it may lye quiet for a time. Perhaps
he may not for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable long ſpace feel any throes, any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94547:5"/> luctations, any rufflings within him, but his Land may
ſeem to be at reſt. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may not enquire at all into his State, or he
may abuſe and delude him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a falſe account of his Condition, or
he may harden his Mind with looſe Atheiſtical Principles, or he may bear
down his Conſcience with a violent Hand, and ſo for a time it may be
ſtill and quiet, like a Clock that ſtands when the Weights are down; but
one time or other the Hand of God will wind it up again, and then every Wheel
and Movement will ſtir to purpoſe: The Eye will mourn, the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head will
bluſh, the Heart will bleed and be very ſore; and yet perhaps the ſenſe
of what he has done will not lead him to true Repentance, but throw him at
laſt into the very Gulph of Deſperation. And therefore we ſhould never be
ſo confident of our own Selves as to do an ill thing: We ſhould not
truſt, no not our own Hearts; becauſe in the end our worſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy will be
that in our own Boſom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94547:6"/> But there are three Caſes eſpecially,
wherein it highly concerns Men to have a <hi>Conſcience void of
Offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> in caſe of Publick Dangers, when the
Face of the World looks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable and diſmal. Seldom do the things of
this Life continue at a ſtay: The ſtate and condition of the World ever and
anon alters, either by means of the different Intereſts and Deſigns of Men,
who labour ſtill to turn the Wheel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, or by the juſt Judgment of God
for Peoples Wantonneſs and Ingratitude in times of outward Proſperity. Now
when Circumſtances are full of Threats and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, they will ſoon ſhew
what the in-ſide of Men is: Conſcience, which in ſuch a Caſe is apt to
tell Guilty Wretches their own, will poſſeſs them with fearful
appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions that God is their Enemy, and that they have no juſt reaſon
to hope for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from Heaven. And what does this naturally tend to, but
to put them on the Rack, when their Fears and their <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94547:6"/> Sins
both haunt them? Whereas an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive Conſcience gives a Man all the
Peace and Security imaginable. For theſe are the ſure Principles on which
he builds his Satisfaction, that God preſides over the World,
ſuperintending and governing all Affairs here below; that not ſo much as a
little Bird falls to the Ground without his Permiſſion; that the very Hairs
of a good Man's head are all number'd; that tho' here we meet with
Tribulations, yet Chriſt hath overcome the World; that he will not ſuffer
us to be tempted above what we are able; and that tho' Extremities ſhould
happen, yet if we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reign with him
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>However ſome are ſo hardy, as to ſcoff at Religion, and
ſtrive to wear out of their Minds the ſenſe of God, yet nothing can carry
a Man out in the Day of Tryal, but ſuch Principles as theſe. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
he be that Relyeth upon theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and upon Examining his Actions,
finds good Reaſons to believe that his <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94547:7"/> Heart is ſincere
and upright, he muſt needs be danger-proof in a very high degree. You have an
inſtance here in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> had bound
themſelves under a Curſe that they would kill him; tho' <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi>
uſed his Authority, and <hi>Tertullus</hi> his Eloquence againſt him; tho'
Men and Devils conſpir'd to deſtroy him, yet his Rejoycing was this, that
his conſtant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe was <hi>to have a Conſcience void of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
toward God, and toward Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, ſuch evil Days and times of Danger every one of us is
very apt to put far off from himſelf, by reaſon of the uncertainty of them:
For as they may, ſo perhaps they may not happen; and every one out of
fondneſs to himſelf, is willing to hope they will not come, at leaſt in
his time. But then,</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> there is another Caſe, which every
day occurs, againſt which a Wiſe Man will be well provided, the Caſe of
Sickneſs; when we ſhould have little elſe to do, but to trim up our
Lamps, and <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94547:7"/> exerciſe our Graces, and ſo to repoſe our
ſelves in the boſom of a faithful God and a merciful Redeemer. Now he that
makes a Conſcience of his ways, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to carry himſelf without
offence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God and Man, will at that time have nothing in compariſon to
do but to wait God's Pleaſure: For as he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees that ſuch a day will
come, ſo he prepares for it before-hand. He is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than to leave the
Great and Heavy Work of eradicating ſinful Habits, and of changing the whole
Frame and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of his Heart, to be done upon a ſick Bed; but takes an
early care to die to the World and to himſelf dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Upon this account, tho'
a Diſeaſe may be very troubleſome and painful, and parting of thoſe old
acquaintances; the Soul and the Body, may be attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with violent Natural
Struglings; yet his Spirit muſt needs be full of Peace; it being
impoſſible that a Courſe of Vertue and Holineſs ſhould bring in any
bitter remembrance at the laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94547:8"/> It was the Prayer of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when
he was bid to ſet his Houſe in order, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38. <hi>Remember
now, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked before Thee in Truth, and with
a perfect Heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> What
unconſionable Man is there in the World, that dares ſay to God in his
Languiſhings? It cannot be, unleſs his Conſcience be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly feared, but
his Heart muſt ake, and his Bowels muſt be full of Gall and Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and
his Soul muſt be ruffled with many diſmal apprehenſions of a Judgment to
come; becauſe his Conſcience, which will then awake, and will ſpeak loud
and home to him, muſt needs tell him, that if he dies, he is undone to all
Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> has rightly obſerved, that God has tinctured
all Wickedneſs with a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Shame and Fear: And certainly there is nothing
like to an Evil Conſcience, to make a Man a Coward, eſpecially when he is
in danger of appearing before the juſt Judge of all the Earth, to whom
Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance belongeth. It is no marvel, if when <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94547:8"/> a Man is
troubled with the Qualms of a ſourc Conſcience, he is more ſick of his
Sins, than his Diſeaſe: If when he ſees Hell open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, he turn
his Face away from that frightful Spectacle, and if he be brought to that
miſerable paſs, that tho' he muſt not ſtay any longer in this World,
yet he knows not how to venture into another.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the neceſſary and natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of an Ill Man;
tho' in time of Health and Gaity, he may drink down mellancholly Thoughts, or
roar his Conſcience into Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or endeavour by lewd Principles to confirm
and harden his Mind againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, yet when the Hand of God comes and
touches him to the Quick, that buſie Thing in his Breaſt will ſtir and
rage, and give him a very bitter Doſe and uneaſie Pillow.</p>
            <p n="3">III. There is another Caſe yet, which I muſt mention,
becauſe from the Higheſt to the Loweſt, we muſt every one of of us come
to it in our order, for it is appointed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Men, once to Die, and after
Death to go to Judgment. And woud we were <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94547:9"/> ſo Provident,
as notwithſtanding the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and Charms of this World, to call our
Thoughts home every Day, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter ſome time for ſuch ſerious
Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as theſe: What is it to Die? Of what infinite Importance is
it to die well? What will become of us when we are dead and gone? What
Eternity, that great thing Eternity means? How unalterable every one's State
will be? And how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it muſt be for us to live over our Lives
again, to rectify thoſe Miſcarriages we are ſuch Fools to be guilty of
now.</p>
            <p>Such Religious Meditations would prove very powerful Reſtraints,
to keep Men within the compaſs of their Duty; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of the Son
of <hi>Sirach; Think on thy latter end; and thou ſhalt never do amiſs.</hi>
What admirable Effects of ſuch Retirements will you not find, when your
laſt Hour ſhall come? For how ſlightly ſoever ſome have ſpoken of
Mortality, I am confident no Man ever yet repented of it on his Death-bed; nor
can any thing be a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Comfort to a Man at the laſt, than to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94547:9"/> conſider that the care of his Life has been to keep <hi>a
Conſcience void of Offence:</hi> 'Tis a Comfort that will ſtick to him to
endleſs Ages.</p>
            <p>Some of the Primitive Writers have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd a few Occaſional
Expreſſions of our Bleſſed Saviour, which we do not find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in
any part of the Sacred Hiſtory of his Life; how they came by them, is not
material for us to enquire: But <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> tells us, this was
one of his Sayings, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>According as I find you at your
Death, ſo I ſhall judge you.</hi> 'Tis like that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
Eccleſ. 11. 3. <hi>In the place where the Tree falleth, there it ſhall
be.</hi> If a Man doth diligently endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perform his Duty in that
manner, and to that extent which the Laws of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do require, his Works
will bear him company to Heaven, and Crown him with unſpeakable Comfort to
all Eternity.</p>
            <p>A good Conſcience is part of that Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet upon which we ſhall
feaſt with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in the Kingdom of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94547:10"/> God; and ſo is a guilty Conſcience part of thoſe
Torments which are the ſad Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Damned. For there is no half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
Houſe between Hell and Heaven, for Men to ſhift themſelves from thoſe
polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wherein they die; nor does Death ſo alter the State of a Man as
that the ſenſe of Guilt and ſting of Conſcience doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ceaſe: No, the Powers and Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul are raiſed and enlarged
upon it's Separation from the Body, and Conſcience becomes more Quick and
Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible than while it was ſrifled and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a heap of Fleſh; ſo
that inſtead of being loſt or abated, the Torments of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience are
aggravated and heightned; and were there no other Fire in Hell, yet that in
ones own Breaſt would yield a Smoke that would aſcend for ever and ever.
<hi>There the Worm dyeth not,</hi> ſaith our Saviour; which may be
underſtood of the Gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Conſcience, as well as of the fearful
Viſitations of an Angry and Juſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94547:10"/> Theſe things being duly conſider'd what
can be ſo adviſeable for us, for the ſecuring of our beſt and deareſt
Intereſt, our Peace in this World and in the next? What can be ſo
neceſſary for us, as to have a Care of our Conſciences, and in
Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and Godly Sincerity to have our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the World? Alas!
we have no abiding place here: The Things of this Life will ſoon ſlip out
of our Hands; that little Good there is in this World we ſhall loſe in a
ſhort time; nor can we carry hence any thing with us, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of
what we have done. And that the Remembrance thereof may not be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I
crave the liberty to offer briefly theſe few things, the Point being
altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Practical.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we give all Moral Diligence to inform our
Conſciences rightly of the Lawfulneſs of all we do. This was the fault of
St. <hi>Paul</hi> before his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, that he took things upon truſt,
and went upon Preſumptions. Had he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently examin'd the Chriſtian
Inſtitution, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94547:11"/> and conſider'd all the Reaſons and
Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on its ſide; he might have been convinc'd of the Truth of it
without a Miracle from Heaven. But he took for granted, that the Moſaical Law
in all its parts was to continue for ever; and ſo he Perſecuted the
Diſciples of Chriſt as Apoſtates from the Law; not looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all this
as injurious Dealing, but as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign Puniſhment. He verily thought
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf bound to do thoſe things: And what a chargeable thought was that
to the Church of Chriſt? What an expence of Blood did it put them to? What
Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments and other Sufferings did it not coſt them, that one Thought
of his?</p>
            <p>Therefore to have <hi>a Conſcience void of Offence,</hi> it is
abſolutely neceſſary to uſe all proper means for the removing and
curing of Miſtakes; ſuch as unprejudiced Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reading of good
Books, conference with skilful and upright Teachers, and the like. For tho' we
are all ſubject to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, by reaſon of our Nature; and tho' there be
few who are not at all miſtaken <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94547:11"/> in one particular or
other; yet as long as a Miſtake is not wilful, proceeding from the Neglect of
proper means, the Man is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted tho' he be Erroneous. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the
ſearcher of Hearts, and the Judge of all the Earth, doth pardon involuntary
Ignorances upon a general Repentance. And this ſhould ever be a fixt Rule for
our Charity to one another, where our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are different, to bear like
Brethren with each others Infirmities, as long as there are tolerable reaſons
to believe that Mens Hearts are ſincere and honeſt, and their Errors
involuntary. However, tho' we live in an uncharitable and cenſorious World,
yet we ſhall be ſure not to miſs of Peace and Satisfaction in our own
Minds, if we be not wanting to our ſelves in our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to inform our
Judgments rightly. A good Conſcience and an Error are not things
inconſiſtent. I am ſure our Apoſtles Errors were in ſome meaſure
wilful, and yet he obtain'd mercy, becauſe what he had done he did through
Ignorance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our endeavours being thus honeſtly <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94547:12"/>
employed, the next way to have a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of Offence,</hi> is to
follow its Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates. Great is the Power which every one's Conſcience hath
over him; and thoſe who ſpeak ſo ſlightingly of its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations,
either have no Conſcience them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or elſe underſtand not what the
Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Power of it is. It hath by the appointment of God himſelf, the
immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Government of us; ſo that the very Word of God doth no otherwiſe
guide us, than by the Light which it affords the Conſcience. Tho' the Divine
Will be the Supreme Rule, yet Conſcience is the inward and immediate
Meaſure of our Actions; and on that account the Command is ſo peremptory,
that every one is to be fully perſwaded in his own Mind; and the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination is ſo poſſitive, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not of Faith, is
Sin. Hence it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently follows that Conſcience muſt be obey'd: For if it
be a ſin to Act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome conviction of the Lawfulneſs of the Action;
what a ſin is it to Act quite contrary to one's Conviction, againſt one's
Judgment and Perſwaſion, and in ſpight of all the Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94547:12"/> and Out-cries of Conſcience, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the direct
unlawfulneſs of what a Man does? All agree that this is utterly
inconſiſtent with a good Conſcience; nay, ſome learned Caſuiſts
tells us, that he is far leſs a Criminal, who committeth Evil when he thinks
it to be Good, than he is who doeth Good when he thinks it to be Evil; for in
the former Caſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is good, but in the Latter the Heart is
obſtinate and perfectly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, as well as the Conſcience
erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</p>
            <p>III. To deſpiſe the World when it ſtands in competition with
our Duty, is another ſure way to keep one's Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of Offence:
Becauſe nothing is more apt to corrupt Mens Minds, and to rifle them of their
Integrity, than the Luſt of the Eyes and the Pride of Life; tho' in the
Judgment of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, it would be the moſt fooliſh
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, to part with one's Soul, tho' to <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94547:13"/> gain the whole
World, were an Acqueſt of that nature poſſible.</p>
            <p>IV. And ſo, to reſiſt the firſt Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto Sin; to
get ſuch a Maſtery over our own Wills, as to arm our ſelves with firm
Purpoſes and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt it: To pray daily and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto
God not to lead us into Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: And above all to have God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways before
our Eyes; to poſſeſs our Souls with a true fear of Him; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
Reverend and Awful thoughts of his Omniſcience and Juſtice; that he is a
Spectator of all our Actions; that He ſearcheth the very Reigns; and that He
looks into all the receſſes of the Heart; and that a time will infallibly
come, when He will Un-caſe us and lay us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and reward every one
according to his Works, and judge even the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Men by <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt:</hi> This alone would be an excellent Means to make Men keep <hi>a
Conſcience void of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> 
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94547:13"/> For they would not
dare to preſume in any kind, did but the true Fear of God rule in their
Hearts kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Becauſe this muſt be granted by all who have any ſenſe
of God, that tho' they may deceive themſelves with lying Hopes, and the
unthinking Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulace with a ſpecious Out-ſide; yet it is impoſſible to
deceive the God of Heaven: Nor can we ſuppoſe any Man to be ſo careleſs
of his own Safety, and Self-Preſervation, as to damn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he doth
verily believe that Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation will be the end of his Evil Works, and that for
all thoſe things God will bring him to Judgment.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, <hi>Whatſoever things are Honeſt, whatſoever
things are Juſt, whatſoever things are Pure and Lovely, and of good Report;
if there be any Virtue, if there be any Praiſe, let us think of thoſe
things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94547:14"/> 
               <hi>And the very God of Peace ſanctifie us
wholly, that our whole Spirit, Soul and Body may be preſerved blameleſs
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; to whom with the Father and the
Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, now and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94547:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
